<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Expressing future plans and arrangements</title>
        <content>
            Present Continuous
            ===================================================================
            Używamy PC gdy mówimy o sprecyzowanych planach - znamy datę i miejsce, wszytsko jest już dopięte na ostatni guzik.
            
            1. I'm seeing Sarah tomorrow. We're having lunch together.
            
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Be going to
            ===================================================================
            Używamy "be going to" gdy mówimy że mamy zamiar coś zrobić, decyzja została już podjeta.
            
            1. I'm going to have my hair cut tomorrow.
            2. She's going to get the last train home.
            
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Present Continuous VS Be going to
            ===================================================================
            Present Continuous wyraża że coś zostało zaplanowane, znamy dokładną datę i godzinę/
            Be going to wyraża intencję, zamiar że coś zostanie zrobione.
            
            I'm meeting Cathy (= we've arranged to meet)
            I'm going to meet Cathy (= it's my intention, but arrangements may or not have been made)
            
            1. I'm meeting Cathy this evening. I'm going to tell her that it's all over.
            
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Future Continuous
            ===================================================================
            1. Używamy gdy mówimy o przyszłych planach.
            
            I will be going to supermarket later - do you want anything?
            
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            2. Czasami gdy chcemy podkreślić że coś się wydarzy bez naszej inicjatywy uzywamy FC.
            
            I'm seeng Sara tomorrow (= I arranged it)
            I'll be seeing Sarah at the party tomorrow (= it will happen anyway, buy I didn't arrange it)
            
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            3. Używamy także gdy chcemy kogoś grzecznie zapytać o zaaranżowanie czegoś (np. spotkania)
            
            Will you be meeting us at the airport?
            
            Present simple
            ===================================================================
            Używamy PS gdy mówimy o cyklicznie powtarzających sie wydarzeniach w teraźnijszości ale także w przyszłosci.
            Np o zaplanowanych w grafiku imprezach, odjazdach autobusów itd.
            
            1. The train leaves in five minutes.
            2. Our classes start next Tuesday.
            
            Inne sposoby wyrażania planów/ustaleń
            ===================================================================
            
            be due to + infinitive (ktoś ma coś zrobić)
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            Używamy gdy mówimy że oczekujemy że ktoś/coś ma coś zrobić
            
            1. My sister is due to arrive at 7.30.
            
            Używamy DUE także gdy mówimy że coś jest spodziewane:
            
            2. The next train is due in five minutes
            
            be about to + infinitive (w najbliżeszj przyszłości)
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            Używamy gdy coś ma się wydarzyć w najbliższej przyszłości
            
            1. My sister is about to have a baby.
            2. We are about to go.
            
            be on the point of + gerund (prawie że już)
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            Używamy bardziej formalnie, gdy coś jest nieuchronne.
            
            1. It is believed that the chancellor is on the point of resignING
            
            be to + infinitive
            ------------------------------------------------------------------
            Używamy formalnie gdy mówimy o oficialnych planach i ustaleniach
            
            1. It has been announced that the Prime Minister IS TO VISIT Malaysia next month.
            
            be to do sth -> ma coś zrobić
            is to visit -> ma odwiedzić
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 6</part>
        <subpart>6A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Ellipsis and substitution</title>
        <content>
            Ellipsis: leaving out subjects and auxiliaries
            ===================================================================
            
            Po AND, BUT, OR, THEN zazwyczaj opuszczamy powtarzajacy się podmiot lub aux. verb. Zwłaszcza gdy zdanie jest krótkie.
            
            1. He got up AND (he) had a shower.
            2. She came to the meeting BUT (she) didn't say anything.
            3. We should phone him OR (we should) send him an e-mail.
            4. We usually have dinner at 10.00 and THEN (we) watch TV.
            
            NIE możemy opuścić powtarzającego się podmiotu lub aux. verb po BEFORE, AFTER, BECAUSE, WHEN, WHILE.
            
            1. They locked the door and windows BEFORE THEY left.
            2. We'll have a look at the photos AFTER WE finish dinner.
            3. He's stressed BECAUSE HE has too much work.
            4. She was horrified WHEN SHE saw the mess he had left.
            5. I met Sam WHILE I was working in Italy.
            
            Ellipsis: leaving out verb phrases or adjectives
            ===================================================================
            
            Zazwyczaj opuszczamy powtarzające się frazy, przymiotniki, modale, cz. BE.
            
            Jeśli czasownik którego chcemy zastąpić jest w Present Simple lub Past Simple
            to wtedy zatępujemy za pomocą do/does/did don't/doesn't/didn't
            
            1. Laura HAS NEVER been to the States but her sister HAS (been there).
            2. Gary thinks he'S  right, but he ISN'T (right) 
            3. I thought I WOULD be able to come tonight, but in fact I CAN'T (be able to come).
            4. I know you've never learned to drive, but I really think you should have (learbed to drive).
            5. A. You must see his latest film! B. I already have (seen)
            
            Możemy także opuszczać frazy po bezokoliczniku z TO. (reduce in)
            
            1. I haven't benn to Egypt, but I'd love TO.
            2. The students cheated in the exam, even though I told them NOT TO.
            
            Substitution: so and not
            ===================================================================
            Używamy SO zamiast powtarzać całe zdanie (pozytywne) po czasownikach odnoszących sie do myślenia:
            ASSUME, BELIEVE, EXPECT, GUESS, HOPE, IMAGINE, PRESUME, SUPPOSE, THINK oraz po
            BE AFRAID, APPEAR/SEEM, SAY.
            
            1. I'll have finished the work by Friday, or at least I HOPE SO.
            2. A. Will you be working on Saturday? B. I SUPPOSE SO, unless we get everything done tomorrow.
            3. Mark loves animals, and his sister EVEN MORE SO.
            
            W przeczących zdaniach używamy [+] czasownika + NOT (I hope NOT) z:
            BE AFRAID, ASSUME, GUESS, HOPE, PRESUME, SUSPECT.
            
            Używamy [-] czasownika + SO (I don't think so) z:
            BELIEVE, EXPECT, IMAGINE, THINK/\.
            
            1. A. Do you think it'll rain tonight? B. I HOPE NOT.
            2. A. She's not very likely to pass, is she? B. No, I'm AFRAID NOT.
            3. The children may be back, but I DON'T THINK SO.
            4. I know she liked the present, even though she DIDN'T SAY SO.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 6</part>
        <subpart>6B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Emphasis (2): cleft sentences</title>
        <content>
            Jeśli chcemy skupić uwagę lub uwypuklić jedną część zdania możemy to zrobić 
            przez dodanie określonych słów lub frazy do początku zdania.
            Taki zabieg nazywa się cleft sentence.
            
            
            1. WHAT / ALL - jedynie ...
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            I need a coffe                      What I need is a coffe
            I don't like the weather here       What I don't like here is the weather.
            I just want to travel               All I want is to travel.
            I only touched it!                  All I did was touch it.
            
            2. WHAT happenS IS / WHAT happenED WAS - co się wydarzy to ... / co się wydarzyło to ...
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            You do a test and then you          What happens is (that) you do a test
            have an interview.                  and then you have a interview.
            
            We left our passports at home       What happened was we left our passports at home.
            
            3. THE PERSON WHO ... / The place where / The first/last time / The reason why ... (Osoba która, z którą ... itd.)
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            I spoke to the manager              The person who I spoke to was the manager.
            We stayed in a five star hotel      The place where we stayed was a five star hotel.
            I last saw him on Saturday          The last time I saw him was on Saturday.
            I bought it because it was cheap    The reason why I bought it was that it was cheap.
            
            4. IT
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            A boy in my class won the prize     It was a boy in my class who won the prize.
            We had the meeting last Friday      It was last Fiday when we had a meeting.
            They charged us extra for wine      It was the wine that they charged us extra for.
            
            It was my parents - po it uzywamy was mimo ze mówimy o liczbie mnogiej - parents.
            It was ME - zamiast it was I.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 6</part>
        <subpart>6C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>