<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Nouns compound and possessive forms</title>
        <content>
            Apostrophe S
            ===================================================================
            
            Posiadanie możemy wyrazić na kilka sposobów:
            
            Dodając 's gdy coś należy do konkretnej osoby, zwierzęcia, organizacji, miejsca.
            
            1. I borrowed my father'S car.
            2. I trod on the cat'S tail.
            3. The company'S head office is in NY.
            4. Zalacain is one of Madrid'S most famous restaurants.
            
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Dodanie 'S vs SAMEGO APOSTROFU na końcu
            
            1. Gdy imię lub pojedyńczy rzeczownik kończy się na S dodajemy 'S. 
                (It's Chris'S book) lub samo ' (Chris' book)
            2. Do mnogich rzeczowników dodajemy SAM APOSTROF po S. 
                (It's my friends' wedding.  It's cats' bowls)
            3. Do nieregularnych mnogich rzeczowników dodajemy 'S na końcu (people, children, men, women etc.) 
                (That's the children'S room. It was a women'S film)
            4. Gdy w zdaniu jest wymienionych kilka osób 'S dodajemy tylko do ostatniej wymienionej 
                (The blonde girl is Alex and Maria'S daughter)
            5. Gdy mówimy o miejscu zamieszkania lub sklepie omijamy słowo house lub shop wstawiając jedynie 'S lub '.
                (We had dinner at Tom's last night)
                (My mother is at the hairdresser's)
            
            OF (insted of apostrophe 's) - przynależność rzeczy do rzeczy
            ===================================================================
            
            1. Używamy zazwyczaj OF zamiast 's gdy dana rzecz przynależy do innej rzeczy.
            
            Can you remember the name OF the film?
            My brother lives at the end OF the road.
            The problem OF old age are many and varied.
            
            2. Używamy OF aby podkreślić przynależność w długich zdaniach.
            
            Helen is the sister OF my cousin in ROME I told you about.
            
            3. Z FRIEND, zazwyczaj używamy A FRIEND OF + name/noun + 'S
            
            Jim is A FRIEND OF OF MY BROTHER'S.
            
            COUPOUND NOUNS (rzeczowniki złożone)
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy rzeczowników złożonych zamiast określać posiadanie za pomocą 's lub of 
            gdy mówimy o ludziach lub przedmiotach do czego są używane, z czego są zrobione, jak pracują, jakiego są rodzaju.
            Drugi rzeczownik zazwyczaj jest główną rzeczą, osobą a pierwszy określa jakieś jego cechy.
            
            np. Tin opener, history teacher, clothes shop.
            
            1. I need the TIN OPENER. Do you know where it is?
            2. I bought a huge FLOWER POT in a GARDEN CENTRE near my house.
            3. My brother is a COMPANY DIRECTOR and my sister is a HISTORY TEACHER.
            4. I opened the CAR DOOR, got in, and put on my SEAT BELT.
            
            
            Różnica między COUPOUND NOUNS  a OF
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            A WINE BOTTLE - oznacza bardziej butelkę niż jej zawartość - zawartość w tym kontekście jest pusta - czyli w wolnym tłumaczeniu - pusta butelka po winie
            A BOTTLE OF WINE - oznacza butelkę z winem.
            
            A WINE GLASS - kieliszek do wina
            A GLASS OF WINE - kieliszek z winem
            
            A JAM JAR - słoik po dzemie
            A JAR OF JAM - słoik z dzemem
            
            A PETROL CAN - karnister (pusty)
            A CAN OF PERTROL - karnister z paliwem
            
            A MATCHBOX - pudełko po zapałkach
            A BOX OF MATCHES - pudełko z zapałkami
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>So and Such</title>
        <content>
            Zazwyczaj używamy SO i SUCH z (that) gdy mówimy o konsekwencjach lub efekcie czegoś.
            Pomijamy (that) gdy mówimy nieformalnie.
            
            SO + ADJ.
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy SO przed przymiotnikami (adj.) lub przysłówkami (-ly adverb).
            
            1. It was SO COLD (that) we decided not ot play tennis.
            2. Agatha plays SO WELL now (that) it's very difficult to beat her.
            
            SO MUCH / SO MANY
            ===================================================================
            
            Użwyamy SO MUCH z niepoliczalnymi rzeczownikami i SO MANY z liczbą mnogą rzeczowników.
            Można użyć SUCH A LOT OF - zamiast SO MUCH / SO MANY
            
            1. There was SO MUCH NOISE (that) the players couldn't concentrate.
            2. There were SO MANY PEOPLE outside the stadium (that) we couldn't find each other.
            3. I had SUCH A LOT OF work (that) I had to stay at the office late.
            
            SUCH (+) A/AN + ADJ. + NOUN
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy SUCH A/AN + ADJ. + singular countable noun.
            
            1. It was SUCH AN EXCITING MATCH (that) I didn't want it to end.
            
            Użwyamy SUCH + ADJ. + uncountable or plural noun
            
            1. It was SUCH AWFUL WEATHER (that) the match had to be cancelled.
            2. They were both SUCH GREAT PLAYERS (that) everyone wanted to see the final.
            
            SO + ADJ. vs SUCH + NOUN
            ===================================================================
            
            Zazwyczaj używamy SO + ADJ. i SUCH  + NOUN bez that jako wytłumaczenia.
            
            1. It was SUCH A LOVELY DAY!
            2. She's SO MEAN!
            3. They're SUCH NICE PEOPLE!
            
            UWAGA !!!
            ===================================================================
            
            1. Możemy użyć SO + ADJ./ADVERB na początku zdania ale wtedy czasownik zostaje przeniesiony.
            SO SUCCESSFUL WAS the first night that people flocked to see the play.
            
            2. SUCH AS = FOR EXAMPLE.
            He loves winter sports, SUCH AS skiing and skating.
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Comparison</title>
        <content>
            Modifiers with AS ... AS ...
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy modyfikatorów ALMOST, JUST, NEARLY, HALF, TWICE, THREE TIMES itd.
            z AS ... AS ...
            
            Można użyć SO zamiast pierwszego AS w zaprzeczeniach: She is not nearly SO difficult AS people say.
            
            1. My sister's ALMOST AS tall AS me / ALMOST AS tall AS I am.
            2. She's JUST AS bossy AS when she was a child.
            3. Their house is NEARLY AS big AS yours.
            4. His latest film isn't HALF AS good AS his previous one.
            
            TWICE możemy użyć tylko przed AS ... AS, THREE TIMES, FOUR TIMES itd możemy użyć z AS ... AS 
            lub z COMPARATIVE ADJ. lub ADVERB: The holiday cost THREE TIMES MORE THAN I'd expected.
            
            5. Our new flat is TWICE AS big AS our old one.
            6. The holiday cost THREE TIMES AS MUCH AS I'd expected.
            
            Modifiers with COMPARATIVE ADJ. or ADVERBS
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy FAR, MUCH lub A LOT + COMPARATIVE ADJ. lub ADVERB dla dużych różnic.
            
            1. The French wine is FAR MORE EXPENSIVE than the South African.
            2. The play was MUCH BETTER than I'd expected.
            3. He's driving A LOT MORE CAREFULLY since he go points on his licence.
            
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Gdy używamy MORE + NOUN dla dużych różnic możemy użyć MUCH / FAR / A LOT MORE + niepoliczalny rzeczownik
            lub MANY / FAR/ A LOT MORE + policzalny rzeczownik w liczbie mnogiej.
            
            1. She earns MUCH MORE MONEY than I do.
            2. Women today have MANY MORE OPPORTUNITIES than they used to.
            
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Używamy SLIGHTY, A LITTE lub A BIT + COMPARATIVE ADJ. lub ADVERB dla małych różnic.
            
            1. She's A LITTLE BETTER than she was yesterday.
            2. The later train is SLIGHTLY CHEAPER than the earlier on.
            3. Could you talk A BIT MORE QUIETLY, please? I'm trying to concetrate.
            
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Gdy używamy MORE + NOUN dla małych różnic, możemy uzyć:
            A LITTLE MORE / SLIGHTLY MORE/ A BIT MORE + NIEPOLICZALNE rzeczowniki
            A FEW MORE / SLIGHTLY MORE / A BIT MORE + POLICZALNE rzeczowniki
            
            1. A: Would you like some more COFFEE? B: Just A LITTLE MORE, please.
            2. We've only got A FEW MORE MINUTES before the show starts.
            
            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Czasami powtarzamy COMPERATIVE ADJ. dla podkreślenia.
            
            1. The taxi driver drove FASTER AND FASTER.
            2. It's getting MORE AND MORE DIFFICULT to make ends meet nowadays.
            
            Modifiers with superlatives
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy BY FAR / MUCH / EASILY / NEARLY / ALMOST aby zmodyfikować stopień najwyższy przymiotników.
            
            1. It was BY FAR THE NICEST of all the hotels we stayed at.
            2. She's MUCH THE PRETTIES of the three children.
            3. That was EASILY THE BEST fish I've had for ages.
            4. I'm NEARLY THE OLDEST in my class.
            
            the ... the ... + comparatives
            ===================================================================
            
            Używamy the ... the ... gdy coś zmienia się wraz z czymś innym
            
            1. THE MORE DANGEROUS a sport (is), THE MORE EXCITING it is to watch.
            2. THE BIGGER the car (is), THE MORE EXPENSIVE it is to run.
            3. THE FASTER I speak Enlish, THE MORE MISTAKES I make.
            4. A: When do you want me to do it? B: THE SOONER THE BETTER.
            5. THE MORE COFFEE you drink, THE LESS WELL you sleep.
            6. THE MORE THE MERRIER.
            7. THE BIGGER THE BETTER.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>