<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Narrative tenses: Describing specific incidents in the past</title>
        <content>
            Narrative tenses: Describing specific incidents in the past
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy Past Simple kiedy opowiadamy o głównym wątku historii, głównej akcji.

            1. This happened when I was about five years old.

            Past Continuous gdy opisujemy pewien stan w przeszłości
            lub gdy  mówimy o wydarzeniu które trwało przez pewna chwilę.

            1. We were sleeping on my parents' bedroom.
            2. Somebody was standing at the end of my bed.

            Past Perfect lub Past Perfect Continuous używamy gdy mówimy o przeszłości,
            która wydażyła się przed głównym wątkiem / akcją w historii.

            1. My father had gone away ...
            2. I had been reading a story.

            ====================================================================

            USED TO / WOULD / ALWAYS + PAST CONT.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            USED TO + Infinitive
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy do określenia czynności które często / powtarzalnie wykonywaliśmy w przeszłości.

            1. I USED TO WALK to the harbour every morning.

            Używamy USED TO gdy mówimy o sytuacjach w przeszłości które się zmieniły porównując ze stanem obecnym.

            2. I USED TO HAVE longer hair when I was younger.

            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            WOULD + Infinitive
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy WOULD + Infinitive w tych samych sytuacjach co USED TO ale gdy używamy czasownika dynamicznego

            1. I WOULD never READ them a book.
            2. She WOULD always MAKE them UP.

            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            ALWAYS + PAST CONTINUOUS
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy gdy mówimy o czynnościach powtarzanych w przeszłości ale które nas DENERWOWAŁY / IRYTOWAŁY.

            1. My friends WERE ALWAYS TEASING me. (teasing = dokuczać)

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 2</part>
        <subpart>2A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Distancing</title>
        <content>  
            SEEM / APPEAR
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy SEEM / APPEAR gdy dystansujemy się od czegoś. Nie jesteśmy pewni że jest to prawda

            IT seems / appear + that + zdanie. (IT seems that somebody do sth)
            Podmiot + seem / appear + bezokolicznik. (He/SHE/IT seems to be ...)

            It SEEMS / APPEARS (that) there is a direct relation between your position in family and your personality.
            New head of department SEEMS / APPEARS TO BE quite friendly.
            Excuse me. THERE SEEMS TO BE a mistake with the bill.


            WOULD SEEM/APPEAR
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy WOULD SEEM / APPEAR aby jeszcze bardziej zdystansować się od informacji. Bardziej formalne niż It seems/appears

            It WOULD SEEM / APPEAR (that) Mr Young had been using the company's assets to pay off his private debts.

            ====================================================================

            The PASSIVE with VERBS of saying and reporting

            Kolejną możliwość zdystansowania się od wypowiedzi (szczególnie w pisanym angielskim) to użycie formy biernej (passive form)
            czasowników: say, think etc.

            1. IT + PASSIVE VERB + THAT + clause

            It IS SAID THAT using washing machine saves people time.
            Czasowniki najczęściej występujące: agree, announce, believe, expect, hope, report, say, suggest, think, understand.

            2. Subject + PASSIVE VERB + TO + INFINITIVE

            The director IS EXPECTED TO RESIGN in the next few days.
            The missing couple ARE UNDERSTOOD TO HAVE BEEN LIVING in Panama

            Czasowniki najczęściej występujące: believe, expect, report, say, think, understand

            3. THERE + PASSIVE VERB + TO + INFINITIVE

            THERE ARE THOUGHT TO BE over a thousand species in danger of extinction.

            Porównaj

            IT is said THAT  + there are more than five million people ...) -> IT is said + THAT + zdanie
            THERE are said TO BE more than five milion people ... -> THERE are said + TO + bezokolicznik + zdanie

            ====================================================================

            OTHER distancing expressions: apparently, according to, may/might
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy APPARENTLY (najczęściej na początku zdania) gdy mamy na myśli że o tym czytaliśmy, zasłyszeliśmy gdzieś
            ale nie jesteśmy do tego przekonani (w nieformalnej rozmowie).

            1. APPARENTLY, Mike and Monica have separated.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy ACCORDING TO gdy znamy źródło informacji.
            Uwaga - nie używamy w znaczeniu: According to me - lepiej użyć: In my opinion

            1. According to new research ...
            2. According to american scientist ...
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            MAY / MIGHT

            Użycie MAY / MIGHT także dystansuje nas od informacji.

            1. Dinosaurs MAY have died out due to extremely rapid climate change.
            2. There are rumours that the band MIGHT be planning to re-form.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 2</part>
        <subpart>2B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>GET</title>
        <content>
            GET + rzeczownik może oznaczać:
            receive, bring, fetch, obtain
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. I GOT an email.
            2. Could you GET me some stamps?
            3. How can I GET to Paris?
            4. We can GET the bus.

            ====================================================================

            GET + przymiotnik, BE + przymiotnik = BECOME - stawać się
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1a. It's dark - jest ciemno
            1b. It's getting dark - ściemnia się

            2a. I'm used to the climate in England now. - przywykłem do klimatu w Anglii
            2b. I'm getting use to the climate in England. - przyzwyczajam się do klimatu w Anglii

            3. I seem to have got very forgetful recently.
            4. The trafic gets worse.
            5. I will never get used tto living on my own.

            ====================================================================

            GET + object + infinitive = make sb do sth
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Używamy gdy chcemy kogos przekonać aby coś za nas zrobił.

            1. GET SB TO FIX it.
            2. GET Jane TO FINISH the report.

            ====================================================================

            GET + object + past participle = HAVE + object + past participle
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. I need to GET MY PASSPORT RENEWED.
            2. I'm going to GET MY HAIR CUT next week.

            ====================================================================

            GET + past participle = BE + past participle (bardziej formalnie)
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Możemy użyć GET zamiast BE przy tworzeniu strony biernej.

            1. Did you know Dan GOT SACKED last week?
            2. My husband GOT CAUGHT driving at 150 km/h
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 2</part>
        <subpart>2C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>