<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Linkers</title>
        <content>
            RESULT - rezultat
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. So - (najbardziej popularny łącznik oznaczający -> a więc, zatem)

            It was freezing cold, SO I wore a thick coat.

            2. As a result, therefore, consequently - (bardziej formalne od -> so), zazwyczaj używane na początku zdania lub wyrażenia.

            As a result - w rezultacie ... -> po as a result zawsze występuje BE w jakiejś formie: will be closed, was closed, is close itd...
            Therefore - dlatego ...
            Consequently - w konsekwencji czego ...

            It snowed hard all night. AS A RESULT the airport was closed.
            We regret that you don't have qualificaions, AND THEREFORE / CONSEQUENTLY we are unable to offer you the job.

            3. Therefore / consequently można też używać jako czasowników głównych.

            We have therefore / consequently decided not to offer you the job.

            ====================================================================

            REASON - powód
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. Because, as, since (more formal) - ponieważ.
            Zazwyczaj używane na początku wyrażenia.

            I have stopped writing to her, because/as/since she never answers me.
            As the weather is so awful, we've decided not to go out.

            2. Because of ... , - z powodu + NOUN
            due to (formal), owning to (formal)- z powodu (formalnie) + NOUN

            Używane zazwyczaj przed RZECZOWNIKIEM.

            The plane was late BECAUSE OF THE FOG.
            Flight 341 has been delayed DUE TO / OWNING TO adverse weather conditions

            ====================================================================

            PURPOSE - cel
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. TO, IN ORDER TO, SO AS TO - po to żeby ...
            Po nich zawsze bezokolicznik.

            I did a language course TO/IN ORDER TO/ SO AS TO IMPROVE my English.

            2. Aby zaprzeczyć używamy IN ORDER NOT TO lub SO AS NOT TO - po to żeby nie ...

            She closed the door quietly SO AS NOT TO / IN ORDER NOT TO wake the baby.

            3. SO THAT + ((modal) can/could + verb (czasownik) lub will/would + verb (czasownik)) - w celu aby móc/chcieć/itd ...

            They moved to London SO THAT they COULD see their parents more often.

            Musimy! użyć SO THAT gdy zmieniamy podmiot w zdaniu

            SHE put the rug over the baby SO THAT HE WOULDN'T be cold.

            4. IN CASE + PRESENT SIMPLE - na wypadek (odnosi się do przyszłości ale używamy czasu PRESENT)

            I'm not going to tell Ann IN CASE she TELLS everyone else.

            ====================================================================

            CONTRAST - różnica
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. BUT - ALE, nieformalny najczęsciej używany łącznik.

            We enjoyed the concert BUT we didn't have very good seats.

            YET (formal) - ALE, podobnie jak BUT ale bardziej formalnie.

            Agnes was attracted to the strangers, YET something in her head was telling her not to get close to him.

            HOWEVER / NETHERTHELESS (formal) - JEDNAK - używane na początku zdania, wskazują/łączą na coś ze zdania poprzedniego.
            Po nich występuje przecinek.

            We enjoyed the concert. HOWEVER, we dodn't have very good seats.
            Agnes wa attracted to the stranger. NEVERTHELESS, something in her head was telling her not to e close to him.

            2. ALTHOUGH / EVEN THOUGH / THOUGH - CHOCIAŻ

            EVEN THOUGH - jest bardziej współczujące od ALTHOUGH
            THOUGH - nieformalne

            We enjoyed the concert ALTHOUGH / EVEN THOUGH / THOUGH we didn't have very good seats.

            THOUGH - może być użyte na końcu frazy/zdania jako komentaż

            He's very friendly - a bit mean, THOUGH.

            3. IN SPITE OF, DESPITE ..., DESPITE THE FACT THAT ... - pomimo że ...

            Po IN SPITE OF i DESPITE używamy
                -> gerung - czyli czasownika z końcówką ING
                -> noun   - rzeczownika
                -> THE FACT THAT + całe zdanie zdania

            IN SPITE OF beING attracted to the stranger ...
            DESPITE HER ATTRACTION to the stranger ...
            DESPITE THE FACT THAT she was attracted to the stranger ...

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 1</part>
        <subpart>1A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Have / Have got</title>
        <content>  
            HAVE
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. Używamy HAVE jako głównego czasownika oznaczającego POSIADANIE (HAVE = MAM, POSIADAM)

            They HAVE a large, rather dilapidated country house in Norfolk.

            2. Have + OBJECT ex. have a bath, have a drink, oznacza czynność - może być używane też w Continuous

            Are you HAVING lunch?
            He doesn't HAVE lunch at home.

            3. HAVE jako czasownik pomocniczy w Present Perfect.

            They HAVE BEEN MARRIED for 15 years
            How long HAS Anna BEEN GOING out with James?

            4. HAVE TO - musieć (zobowiązać się do czegoś)

            DO we really HAVE TO do it ?
            I HAD TO do it ?

            5. HAVE + OBJECT + PAST PARTICIPLE - używamy gdy mówimy że zapłaciliśmy / zleciliśmy komuś zrobienie czegoś

            HAVE STH DONE / HAD STH DONE

            We are going to HAVE the kitchen REPAINTED next week.
            I HAD my eyes TESTED when I got my new glasses.
            Where do you HAVE your hair CUT

            ====================================================================

            HAVE GOT
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. HAVE GOT używamy tak samo jak HAVE (HAVE GOT = MAM, POSIADAM)
            - HAVE GOT ma znaczenie teraźniejsze - w czasie przeszłym używamy tylko HAD
            - HAVE GOT jest używane w nieformalnym angielskim.

            How many children HAVE YOU GOT? I HAVE GOT three.

            2. HAVE GOT TO - używa się aby sprecyzować zobowiązania (obligations)

            I HAVE GOT TO make a quick phone call (specific / sprecyzowane).
            I HAVE GOT TO buy birthday present - Używamy na specjalne okazje np: urodiny, gwiazdka itd
            I HAVE TO wear a suit to work (general / ogólne) - Używamy ogólnie - bez specjalnych okazji, więc bez GOT

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 1</part>
        <subpart>1B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Pronouns</title>
        <content>
            GENERIC PRONOUNS
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. YOU - używamy gdy mówimy o ludziach w ogóle / generalnie

            YOU can learn a language faster if you go to live in a country where it is spoken.

            2. ONE + (-S/-ES) 3 forma osobowa - Bardziej formalnie gdy mówimy o ludziach w ogóle, rzadko używany w mówionym angielskim.

            ONE should never criticize without being sure of the facts.
            ONE sayS that eating tomatoes can help protect the body

            3. WE - można używać w odniesieniu do czytelnika / słuchacza

            When WE talk about an accent, WE must not confuse this with pronunciation.

            4. THEY - w nieformalnym angielskim używamy gdy mówimy o ludziach w ogóle / generalnie lub o ludziach u władzy.

            THEY always say ... - (they = people in general)
            THEY should make it ... - (they = government)

            5. THEY / THEM / THEIR - używamy do osoby która może być mężczyzną lub kobietą ale w danej chwili nie wiemy kim jest.

            If someone GOES to live in a foreign country, THEY will have to get uses to a different way of life.
            Could the person who left THEIR bag in the library please come and see me?
            If anyone HAS NOT yet paid THEIR course fees, THEY should go to registration immediately.

            ====================================================================

            REFLEXIVE AND RECIPROCAL (obupólny) PRONOUNS
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. REFLEXIVE PRONOUNS (Yourself, himself, myself, ourselves etc.) - używamy gdy podmiot i obiekt jest tą samą osobą.
            Nie używamy z: WASH, SHAVE, FEEL, RELAX, CONCENTRATE (NOT wash yourself, relax yourself)

            You need to look after YOURSELF.
            He always talks about HIMSELF.

            2. (Yourself, himself, myself etc.) Używamy po przyimkach (preposition).

            I managed to complete the crossword! I was really pleased with MYSELF.

            Po przyimkach MIEJSCA używamy OBJECT PRONOUNS (his/her/my)

            She put the bag next TO HER ON THE SEAT

            3. (Yourself, himself, myself etc.) Używamy gdy chcemy podkreślić / uwypuklić podmiot.

            We decorated the house OURSELVES.
            Do it YOURSELF!

            4. BY + (Yourself, himself, myself etc.) = on your/my own, alone - na własną rękę, samemu

            I don't feel very comfortable going to the cinema BY MYSELF.

            5. EACH OTHER / ONE ANOTHER dla obupólnych akcji - gdy A wywiera akcja na B, B wywiera akcje na A.

            My ex-husband and I don't talk to EACH OTHER any more.
            My mother and sister don't understand ONE ANOTHER at all.

            They bought THEMSELVES some new shoes - A kupiła buty dla A, B kupił buty dla B.
            They bought some new shoes for EACH OTHER - A kupiła buty dla B, B kupił buty dla A.

            ====================================================================

            IT AND THERE
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            1. IT + BE używamy gdy mówimy o czasie, temperaturze i odlegości

            IT's five miles to London.
            IT's 10 o'clock.

            2. IT + BE przed przymiotnikami

            IT was GREAT to hear form you.
            IT is ALRIGHT for those people ...

            3. THERE + BE + NOUN używamy odnośnie ludzi lub rzeczy obecnych, istniejących (lub nie)

            THERE IS a big crowd of people.
            THERE USED TO BE a cinema in that street.
            THERE ARE three meetings this week.
            THERE IS no need to hurry.
            THERE IS a spelling mistake in this word.
            THERE is absolutely nothing interesting in it.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 1</part>
        <subpart>1C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>