<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Linkers</title>
        <content>
            RESULT - rezultat
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. So - (najbardziej popularny łącznik aznaczający -> a więc, zatem)

            It was freezing cold, SO I wore a thick coat.

            2. As a result, therefore, consequently - (mardziej formalne od -> so), zazwyczaj używane na początku zdania lub wyrażenia.

            As a result - w rezultacie ...
            Therefore - dlatego ...
            Consequently - w konsekwencji czego ...

            It snowed hard all night. AS A RESULT the airport was closed.
            We regret that you don't have qualificaions, AND THEREFORE / CONSEQUENTLY we are unable to offer you the job.

            3. Therefore / consequently można też używać jako czasowników głównych.

            We have therefore / consequently decided not to offer you the job.

            ====================================================================

            REASON - powód
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. Because, as, since (more formal) - ponieważ.
            Zazwyczaj używane na początku zdania.

            I have stopped writing to her, because/as/since she never answers me.

            2. Because of ... , - z powodu
            due to (formal), owning to (formal)- z powodu (formalnie)

            Używane zazwyczaj przed rzeczownikiem.

            The plane was late BECAUSE OF THE FOG.
            Flight 341 has been delayed DUE TO / OWNING TO adverse weather conditions

            ====================================================================

            PURPOSE - cel
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. TO, IN ORDER TO, SO AS TO - po to żeby ...
            Po nich zawsze bezokolicznik.

            I did a language course TO/IN ORDER TO/ SO AS TO IMPROVE my English.

            2. Aby zaprzeczyć używamy IN ORDER NOT TO lub SO AS NOT TO - po to żeby nie ...

            She closed the door quietly SO AS NOT TO / IN ORDER NOT TO wake the baby.

            3. SO THAT + ((modal) can/could + verb (czasownik) lub will/would + verb (czasownik)) - w celu aby móc/chcieć/itd ...

            They moved to London SO THAT they COULD see their parents more often.

            Musimy! użyć SO THAT gdy zmieniamy podmiot w zdaniu

            SHE put the rug over the baby SO THAT HE WOULDN'T be cold.

            4. IN CASE + PRESENT SIMPLE - na wypadek (odnosi się do przyszłości ale używamy czasu PRESENT)

            I'm not going to tell Ann IN CASE she TELLS everyone else.

            ====================================================================

            CONTRAST - różnica
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            1. BUT - ALE, nieformalny najczęsciej używany łącznik.

            We enjoyed the concert BUT we didn't have very good seats.

            YET (formal) - ALE, podobnie jak BUT ale bardziej formalnie.

            Agnes was attracted to the strangers, YET something in her head was telling her not to get close to him.

            HOWEVER / NETHERTHELESS (formal) - JEDNAK - używane na początku zdania, wskazują/łączą na coś ze zdania poprzedniego. Po nich występuje przecinek.

            We enjoyed the concert. HOWEVER, we dodn't have very good seats.
            Agnes wa attracted to the stranger. NEVERTHELESS, something in her head was telling her not to e close to him.

            2. ALTHOUGH / EVEN THOUGH / THOUGH - CHOCIAŻ

            EVEN THOUGH - jest bardziej współczujące od ALTHOUGH
            THOUGH - nieformalne

            We enjoyed the concert ALTHOUGH / EVEN THOUGH / THOUGH we didn't have very good seats.

            THOUGH - może być użyte na końcu frazy/zdania jako komentaż

            He's very friendly - a bit mean, THOUGH.

            3. IN SPITE OF, DESPITE ..., DESPITE THE FACT THAT ... - pomimo że ...

            Po IN SPITE OF i DESPITE używamy
                -> gerung - czyli czasownika z końcówką ING
                -> noun   - rzeczownika
                -> THE FACT THAT + całe zdanie zdania

            IN SPITE OF beING attracted to the stranger ...
            DESPITE HER ATTRACTION to the stranger ...
            DESPITE THE FACT THAT she was attracted to the stranger ...





        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 1</part>
        <subpart>1A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>...</title>
        <content>  
            ...
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 1</part>
        <subpart>1B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>...</title>
        <content>    
            ...
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 1</part>
        <subpart>1C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>