<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Perrmission, obligation, and necessity</title>
        <content>
            CAN, MUST, SHOULD, OUGHT TO, HAD BETTER / HAD BETTER NOT
            ===================================================================

            Gdy mówimy że powinniśmy coś wykonać w przeszłości używamy:
            SHOULD HAVE / OUGHT TO HAVE + III FORMA

            1. We should have / ought to have gone home on motorway - it would heve been quicker.

            HAD BETTER jest mocniejsze od should/ought to i używane gdy dajemy komuś radę lub ostrzeżenie.
            Przeczenie do HAD BETTER -> HAD BETTER NOT

            1. You had better post the parcel today or they won't get there in time.

            HAVE TO / HAVE GOT TO
            ===================================================================

            HAVE TO i HAVE GOT TO używamy gdy mówimy o zobowiązaniach, o czymś co musimy wykonać.
            HAVE GOT TO używamy odnośnie specjalnych zobowiązań, HAVE TO przy zwykle powtarających się zobowiązaniach.

            1. All passengers will have to fill in an immigration form on arrival.
            2. I've got to buy a birthday present for my brother.

            NEED / NEEDN'T / NEEDN'T HAVE + III forma
            ===================================================================

            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            NEED / DON'T NEED
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            Używamy gdy coś jest potrzebne/ niepotrzebne przy określonych zwykłych okazjach.

            1. You usually need to check in at least two hours before a flight leaves.
            2. I don't need to take a jacket. It's going to be hot today.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            NEEDN'T + bezokolicznik / DON'T NEED TO
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            NEEDN'T używamy gdy coś nie jest potrzebne w określonych sytuacjach

            1. You needn't lock the car. Nobody will still it in this village.

            DON'T NEED TO używamy gdy mówimy o nawykowych/ogólnych potrzebach

            1. I don't need to wear a glasses. My eyesight is still good.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            NEEDN'T HAVE + III forma
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            NEEDN'T HAVE + III forma, używamy gdy coś nie musieliśmy zrobić ale to zrobiliśmy:

            We needn't have bookED a table. The restaurant is empty. - Nie musieliśmy rezerwować stolika ale i tak zarezerwowwaliśmy
            We didn't need to book a table. The restaurant is empty. - Nie musieliśmy rezerwować stolika i nie zarezerwowaliśmy
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Be ABLE to , be ALLOWED to, be PERMITTED to, be SUPPOSED to
            ===================================================================

            Używamy BE ABLE TO lub BE ALLOWED TO + BEZOKOLICZNIK gdy mówimy że coś jest możliwe lub dozwolone.

            1. From tomorrow we won't be able to park in this street.
            2. You're not allowed to smoke in any public buildings.

            UWAGA !
            Nie używamy IT przed allowed to zamiast tego używamy permitted to
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            BE PERMITTED TO + bezokolicznik, używamy w formalnych sytuacjach gdy mówimy że coś jest dozwolone lub nie przez prawo lub regulacje prawne

            1. It is not permitted to take mobiles into the exam room.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            BE SUPPOSED TO - przypuszczać, zakładać
            Używamy gdy mówimy że coś powinno lub nie powinno być robione z powodu zasad.
            Ale zasady te mogą być złamane.

            1. Students are not supposed to have guests after 12, but everyone does.
            2. We are supposed to check in at 3.30. What's the time now?
            3. You aren't supposed to park here - it's a hospital entrance.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 5</part>
        <subpart>5A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Verbs of the senses</title>
        <content>
            HEAR, SEE, SMELL, FEEL, TASTE
            ===================================================================

            Hear, see, smell, feel, taste to podstawowe czasowniki zmysłów.
            Są one STATYCZNE i zazwyczaj używamy CAN z tymi czasownikami aby określić że słyszymy, widzimy, czujemy itd.

            I can hear you - słyszę Cię.
            We can see you - widzimy Cię.
            Can you see me - widzisz mnie.

            1. I can hear a noise downstairs.
            2. Can you see the blue circle?
            3. I can smell burning.
            4. I can't taste the garlic in the soup.

            Nie używamy zazwyczaj tych czasoników w formie ciągłej (continous).

            HEAR, SEE mogą być także dynamiczne i wtedy możemy ich użyć w formie ciągłej ale znaczenie jest już inne.

            1. I've been hearing good news - Zasłyszałem dobre wieści.
            2. I'm seeing James tonight - Widze się z James'em dzisiaj wieczorem (Mam z nim zaplanowane spotkanie)

            ===================================================================

            SEE, HEAR + INFINITIVE or GERUND
            ===================================================================

            See / hear + OBJECT + VERB (INFINITIVE) - Gdy widzieliśmy/słyszeliśmy całą sytuację/ akcję
            See / hear + OBJECT + VERB (GERUND) - Gdy widzieliśmy/słyszeliśmy sutuację/akcję w trakcie trwania (in progress)


            1. I hear the girl play a piece by Chopin - Słyszałem jak zagrała Chopina (cały utwór słyszałem).
            2. I hear the girl playing a piece by Chopin - Słyszałem jak grała Chopina (przez jakiś okres czasu słyszałem).

            1. I saw the man hit his dog - Widziałem jak mężczyzna uderzył swojego pasa.
            2. I saw the man hitting his dog - Widziałem jak mężczyzna bił swojego psa.

            Tak samo możemy postępować z WATCH i NOTICE.

            ===================================================================

            LOOK, FEEL, SMELL, SOUND, TASTE + ADJ/NOUN
            ===================================================================

            Jeśli mówimy o wrażeniu które coś lub ktoś na nas wywarł to używamy LOOK, FEEL, SMELL, SOUND, TASTE.
            Po tych czasownikach możemy użyć:

            1. ADJECTIVE,

            You look tired. That smells delicious. This music sounds awful.
            These shoes feel uncomfortable. The soup tastes a bit salty.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            2. LIKE + A NOUN,

            You look like your mother. It sounds like thunder. This tastes like tea, not coffee.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            3. AS IF / AS THOUGH + A CLAUSE
            She looked as if / as though she had been crying.
            It sounds as if / as though someone is trying to open thedoor.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            4.
            TASTE OF - smakuje czymś - Soup has the taste of garlic - smakuje czosnkiem, jest w niej czosnek (pomidorowa)
            TASTE LIKE - smakuje jak - Soup taste like garlic - smakuje jak czosnek (czosnkowa)

            This smells / tastes of garlic.
            This smells like garlic

            ===================================================================

            SEEM
            ===================================================================

            Używamy SEEM gdy coś/ktoś sprawia wrażenie że coś robi - Np wrażenie że jest zmartwiony.
            Porównaj look z seem:

            1. You look worried = I get the impression from your face.
            2. You seen worried = I get impression from the wat you are behaving in general, e.g. voice, actions ...

            Po SEEM można użyć

            1. ADJECTIVE

            You seem worried.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            2. INFINITIVE

            You seem to be a bit down today.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            3. LIKE + NOUN / AS IF / AS THOUGH + VERB PHRASE

            It seemed like a good idea at the time, but in fact it wasn't
            It seems as if / as though every time I clean the car it rains.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            UWAGA!
            SEEM nie używamy w formie ciągłej.

            ===================================================================
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 5</part>
        <subpart>5B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Gerunds and infinitives</title>
        <content>
            being done / to be done
            ===================================================================

            Używamy biernego (gerund) czas. z końcówką ING (BEING DONE) lub biernego bezokolicznika (TO BE DONE)
            gdy mówimy o zdarzeniu które zostało zrobione przez podmiot.

            1. She LOVES BEING TOLD how pretty she is.
            2. I'm tired OF BEING LIED TO. I want the truth.
            3. It's very DIFFICULT TO GET PROMOTED in this company.
            4. My car NEEDS TO BE SERVICED.
            5. I'm fed up WITH BEING TOLD what to wear.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            having done / to have done
            ===================================================================

            Używamy (perfect gerund) HAVING DONE lub (perfect infinitive)
            gdy chcemy podkreślić że akcja została zakończona lub odbyła się w przeszłości.

            1. He thanked them for HAVING HELPED him.
            2. HAVING STUDIED one language before makes it easier to learn another.
            3. How wonderful TO HAVE FINISHED all our exams!
            4. By the time I'm 30, I hope TO HAVE STARTED a family.

            Zazwyczaj nie ma wielkiej różnicy czy używamy simple gerund lub infinitive i perfect gerund lub infinitive.

            He denied STEALING / HAVINGS STOLEN the money.
            It was our fault. We were silly NOT TO LOCK / NOT TO HAVE LOCKED the car.
            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            WOULD LIKE, WOULD LOVE, WOULD HATE, WOULD PREFER, WOULD RATHER
            ===================================================================
            Używamy perfect gerund (HAVING DONE) po WOULD LIKE, WOULD LOVE, WOULD HATE, WOULD PREFER oraz WOULD RATHER.

            I would like to see the Eiffel Tower = when I go to Paris in the future.
            I would like to have seen the Eiffel Tower = I was in Paris, but I didn't see it.

            1. I would like to have seen your face when they told you you'd won the competition.
            2. We would rather have stayed in a more centrla hotel - Po WOULD RATHER nie ma ani Gerund ani TO.

            TO BE + verb + -ing
            ===================================================================

            Używamy ciągłego bezokolicznika (TO BE + verb + -ing) aby powiedzieć że akcja jest w toku w momencie mówinia o niej.

            1. I would like to be lying on the beach right now.
            2. She seems to be coughing a lot - do you think she's OK?

            Inne przypadki użycia Gerunds i Infinitives
            ===================================================================

            Używamy GERUND po określonych wyrażeniach z IT lub THERE:

            It's no use.
            There's no point.
            It's not worth.

            1. It's no use worryING.
            2. Is there any point in askING him?
            3. It's no good talkING

            Używamy INFINITIVE po rzeczownikach stworzonych z czasowników np: agree, plan, hope.

            1. We had an AGREEMENT TO SHARE the costs.
            2. Our PLAN it TO LEAVE on Saturday.

            Używamy INFINITIVE po kwantyfikatorach: enough, too much, a lot, plenty of

            1. There is too much to see.
            2. There wasn't enought snow for us to ski.

            Używamy INFINITIVE po something, anywhere.

            1. Is there anything to eat?
            2. There is nowhere to go at night.

            Używamy INFINITIVE po pytajnikach (za wyjątkiem Why)

            1. I don't know where to go or what to do.

            Używamy INFINITIVE po superlatywach i first, second, last itd.

            1. Who was the first person to walk on the moon?
            2. He's the youngest player ever to play for England.

            Tabela gerung / infinitive (podstawowe)
            ===================================================================

            Gerung:

            enjoy - enjoy living
            fancy - fancy seeing
            discuss - discussed going
            dislike - dislike watching
            finish - finished preparing
            mind - don't mind doing
            suggest - suggested staying
            recommend - recommended meeting
            keep - kept working
            avoid - avoid talking

            Infinitive:

            agree - agreed to give
            ask - asked to leaved
            decide - decided to go
            help - help to clean
            plan - plan to buy
            hope - hope to pass
            learn - learning to sing
            want - want ot come
            would like - would like to see
            promise - promised not to be

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 5 Advanced - Unit 5</part>
        <subpart>5C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>