<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Third Conditional (3 warunkowy)</title>
        <content> 
            IF + Had + III forma czasownika, would + have + III forma czasownika
            
            If I'd know about the meeting, I would have gone.
            If I hadn't gone to that party, I wouldn't have met my wife.
            You wouldn't have been late if you had got up earlier.
            We would have arrived at 6.00 if we hadn't got lost.
            
            skrót od had to 'd
            
            3 warunkowego - używamy gdy spekulujemy, mówimy o hipotetycznej sytuacji w przeszłości (która się nie wydarzyła).
            
            Yesterday I got up late and missed my train (prawdziwa sytuacja)
            If I hadn't got up late yesterday, I wouldn't have missed my train (hipotetyczna sytuacja)
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Question tags, indirect questions</title>
        <content> 
            Positive ver, negative tag.
            
            It's cold today, isn't it?
            You're Polish, aren't you?
            They live in Ankara, don't they?
            The match finishes at 8.00, doesn't it?
            She worked in a bank, didn't she?
            We've mer before, haven't we?
            You'll be OK, won't you?
            
            Negative verb, positive tag
            
            She is not here today, is she?
            You aren't happy, are you?
            They don't smoke, do they?
            She doesn't eat meat, does she?
            You did not like the film, did you?
            She hasn't been to Rome before, has she?
            You won't tell me, will you?
            
            Negatywny tag gdy zdanie jest pozytywne, pozytywny tag gdy zdanie negatywne.
            
            Indirect questions
            
            direct question / indirect question
            Where's the bank / Could you tell me where the bank is?
            What time do the shops close / Do you know what time the shops close?
            Is there a bus stop near here / Do you know if there is a bus stop near here?
            Does this train go to Victoria? / Could you tell me if this train goes to Victoria?
            
            Aby uczynić pytanie bardziej grzecznym używamy Could you tell me ... ? lub Do you know ... ?
            Zmienia się wtedy kolejność  na Podmiot + czasownik
            Do you know WHERE THE POST OFFICE IS?
            
            Używamy również tej struktury przy Can you remember ... ?
            Can you remember where he lives?
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Phrasal verbs</title>
        <content> 
            Grupa pierwsza
            NO object - verb and up, on, etc. - CAN'T be separated.
            
            COME ON! HURRY UP! We're late.
            The plane TOOK OFF two hours late.
            GO AWAY and never COME BACK!
            
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            Grupa druga
            WITH object - verb and up, on etc. - CAN'T be separated.
            
            I'm LOOKING FOR my key. (nie może być: I'm looking my key for.)
            I ASKED FOR chicken, not steak.
            Please LOOK AFTER the baby.
            I don't GET ON WITH my sister.
            I'm LOOKING FORWARD TO the party.
            
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            Grupa trzecia
            WITH object - verb and up, on etc. - CAN be separated.
            
            Please switch off your phone / Please switch your phone off / Please switch it off.
            Can you fill in this form, please?/ Could you fill this form in, please? / Could you fill it in, please?
            They've set up a new company / They've set new company up. / They have set it up.
            Don't throw away those papers / Don't throw those papers awat / Don't throw it away.
            
            W grupie trzeciej jeśli obiekt jest zaimkiem (it, him, her etc.) wtedy musimy go wstawić za czasownik
            Swich IT off.
            Set IT up.
            Give IT back.
            Throw them away.
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>