<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>must, have to shoul (obligation)</title>
        <content>    
            content
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>must, may, might, can't (deduction)</title>
        <content>    
            MUST - używamy gdy jesteśmy pewni że mamy rację:
            They must be out. There aren't any light on.
            She must have a lot of money
            
            MAY / MIGHT - używamy gdy myślimy że coś jest prawdopodobne
            His phone's switched off. He might be on the plane now.
            She might not like that skirt. It's not her style.
            She's not at home. She may be working.
            He hasn't written. He may not have my address.
            
            CAN'T - używamy gdy jesteśmy pewni że coś jest niemożliwe / nieprawdziwe
            It can't be true.
            He can't be ill. I saw him at the gym.
            They can't be Italian. They're speaking to each other in Spanish.
            
            W tym kontekście, przeciwnością MUST jest CAN'T a nie mustn't
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>can, could, be able to (ability and possibility)</title>
        <content>    
            CAN / COULD
            I can speak Spanish very well
            She could play the violin when she was three
            She can't come tonight. She's ill.
            They couldn't wait becouse they were in a hurry
            Could you ipen that door, please?
            
            CAN - jest czasownikiem modalnym. Ma tylko formę Present, Past i formę warunkową (Conditional Form) (ale może być też użyte w formie przyszłej).
            Dla innych czasów używamy BE ABLE TO.
            
            BE ABLE TO
            I am able to accept your invitation.
            There weren't able to come.
            I'll be able to practise my English in London.
            She has been able to speak French since she was a child.
            I'd like to be able to ski.
            I love being able to sleep late at weekends
            
            Można używać BE ABLE TO w czasie Present, Past, Future, Present Perfect jako rzeczownik odsłowny lub bezokolicznik
            BE ABLE w Present i Past jest bardzo formalny, dużo bardziej formalny niż CAN i COULD
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3B</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>