<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>First conditional and future time clauses + when, until, etc</title>
        <content> 
            IF (or UNLESS = IF NOT) + Present Simple, WILL/WON'T + Infinitife
            
            If you don't do more work, you'll fail the exam.
            He'll be late for work if he doesn't hurry up.
            She won't get into university unless she gets good grades.
            
            Używamy Present Simple po IF.
            
            Unless = if not 
            (I won't go unless she invites me. = I won't go if she doesn't invite me.)
            
            Można użyć trybu ROZKAZUJĄCEGO wzamian za czas przyszły !!! 
            (Come and see us next week if you have time)
            (As soon as you get your exam results, call me)
            
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Future time clauses
            
            As soon as you get your exam results, call me.
            We'll have dinner when your father gets home.
            I won't go to bed until you come home.
            I'll have lunch before I leave.
            After I finish university, I'll probably take a year off and travel.
            
            Używamy Present Simple (tak jak po IF) po:
            when, as soon as, until, before, after
            
            when - kiedy
            as soon as - jak tylko
            until - dopóki, aż do - po tym słówku jest zawsze zdanie twierdzące (UWAGA ! po dopóki w polskim jest zawsze przeczenie, w angielskim jest inaczej)
            before - przed
            after - po
            
            I'll call you as soon as I arrive (mówimy w kontekście przyszłości ale używamy Present simple bo 'po as soon as' nie może być will)
            I won't go to bed until you come home (po until zawsze zdanie twierdzące)   
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Second Conditional</title>
        <content> 
            IF + past simple, would/wouldn't + infinitive
            
            If I had more money, I'd buy a bigger house.
            If he spoke English, he could get a job in a hotel.
            I would get on better with my parents if I didn't live with them.
            I wouldn't do that job inless yhey paid me a really good salary.
            If I were you, I'd buy a new computer.
            
            Second Conditional używamy gdy mówimy o sytuacjach hipotetycznych / gdybamy o czymś.
            I don't have much money, so I can't buy a bigger house (real situation) - Nie mam dużo pieniędzy, więc nie kupie większego mieszkania (sytuacja realna)
            If I had more money, I'd buy a bigger house (hipothetical) - Gdybym miał więcej pieniędzy, kupiłbym większy dom. (gdybanie)
            
            Konstrukcji IF I WERE YOU, I'D ... używamy do dawania rad (nie można użyć If I was you -> to jest błąd!)
            
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Would/wouldn't + infinitive
            
            My ideal holiday would be a week in the Bahamas.
            I'd never buy a car as big as yours.
            
            Możemy użyć WOULD/WOULDN'T + infinitive (bez "If") gdy mówimy o sytuacji hipotetycznej, wyobrażamy sobie coś, gdybamy.
            
            --------------------------------------------------------------------
            
            Różnica pomiędzy I a II Conditional-em
            
            If I have time, I'll help you (a possible situation. I may have time) = Jeśli będę miał czas to Ci pomogę (sytuacja możliwa. Możliwe że będę miał czas)
            
            If I had time, I'd help you. (an imaginary situation. I don't / won't have time) = Gdybym miał czas to bym Ci pomógł (sytuacja hipotetyczna / gdybanie. Nie mam / nie będę miał czasu)
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4B</subpart>
    </grammary>
        <grammary>
        <title>Usually and used to</title>
        <content>
            USUALLY 
            Present habits and states (Obecne przyzwyczajenia i stany)
            
            I usually get up at 8.00 on school days.
            I don't usually go out during the week.
            Houses in the suburbs usually have gardens.
            Do you usually walk to work?
            
            USED TO
            Past habits and states (Przeszłe przyzwyczajenia i stany)
            
            We used to be close friends but we don't see each other any more.
            I used to go out with that girl when I was at school.
            Did you use to wear glasses?
            She didn't use to have fair hair. She had dark hair before.
            
            Dla teraźniejszych nawyków używamy USUALLY / NORMALLY + present simple.
            Dla przeszłych nawyków używamy USED To / DIDN'T USE TO + invinitive.
            
            Używamy USED TO dla czynniści które były prawdziwe przez dłuższy okres czasu w przeszłości, ale teraz już nie są prawdziwe.
            I used to wear glasses. But now I don't any more.
            I used to smoke = Paliłem przez jakiś okres czasu w przeszłości ale teraz nie pale
            
            Aby podkreślić różnicę że coś miało miejsce kiedyś ale teaz już nie używamy słówek: not ... any more / any longer ( = not now) + present simple
            I use to go to the gym but I don't any more / any longer.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 3 Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>