<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Passive voice</title>
        <content>
            Present Simple:

            Letters ARE deliverED twice a day.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Present Continuous:

            The suspect IS BEING questionED by the police.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Past Simple:

            The bus WAS stoppED by us.
            The programme WAS first BROADCAST in 1998.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Past Continuous:

            Our hotel room WAS BEING cleanED when we arrived
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Present Perfect:

            My car HAS BEEN STOLEN.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Past Perfect:

            They HAD BEEN warnED about the danger.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Future:

            You will be PAID on Friday.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Modal verbs:

            This meat MUST BE cookED for at least an hour.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            ===================================================================

            Czasowniki z dwoma dopełnieniami:

            Lady Markham's late husband GAVE THE PAINTING TO THE GALLERY.
            Lady Markham's late husband GAVE THE PAINTING THE GALLERY.

            1. THE PAINTING WAS GIVEN to gallery by her late husband.
            2. THE GALLERY WAS GIVEN the painting by her late husband.

            Gdy jedno z dopełnień jest osobą to bardziej naturalne jest że staje się podmiotem:

            BOBBY WAS GIVEN a new bike for his birthday.
            a nie:
            A NEW BIKE WAS GIVEN to Bobby for his birthday.

            ===================================================================

            Passive form:
            think, believe, report, consider, know, say, expect + infinitive

            -------------------------------------------------------------------
            Gdy wydarzenie w czasie TERAŹNIEJSZYM to: passive + infinitive:

            The Queen IS THOUGHT TO BE one of the richest people.
            Mr Smith IS BELIEVED TO BE STAYING with friends.
            -------------------------------------------------------------------

            Gdy wydarzenie w czasie PRZESZŁYM to: passive + past infinitive (have + past participle)

            This ship IS REPORTED TO HAVE SUNK.
            Many people ARE THOUGHT TO HAVE DROWNED.

            ===================================================================

            HAVE / GET STH DONE

            Gdy mówimy że ktoś zrobił coś DLA nas np. za pieniądze.

            I don't know how to repair cars, so I'M HAVING MINE REPAIRED at the garage round the corner.
            I really must GET MY EYES TESTED. I'm sure I need glasses. GET YOUR HAIR CUT!

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>Masterclass - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>1</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>
