<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Can / could, be able to, manage to, succeed in doing sth</title>
        <content>
            CAN

            Używamy CAN gdy mówimy o:
            możliwościach, umiejętnościach,
            żądaniach, prośbach,
            gdy prosimy o pozwolenie

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Możliwości, umiejętności:

            She can drive a car
            John can speak Spanish.
            I cannot hear you. (I can't hear you.)
            Can you hear me ?

            Zazwyczaj używamy CAN w czasie teraźniejszym (present), możliwe jest też użycie CAN gdy dokonujemy decyzji w teraźniejszości,
            która ma wpływ na przyszłość:

            Can you help me with my homework (present)
            I'm too busy today. But I can help you tomorrow (future)

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Żądania, prośby:

            Can you make a cup of coffee, please.
            Can you put the TV on.
            Can you come here a minute.
            Can you be quiet.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Pośba o pozwolenie, wydanie pozwolenia lub jego odmowa:

            Can I smoke in this room?
            You can't smoke here, but you can smoke in the garden.

            W powyższym przypadku możemy użyć COULD, MAY, MIGHT dla pozwoleń, użycie CAN jest nieformalne.

            ===================================================================

            COULD

            Używamy gdy mówimy o:
            możliwościach, umiejętnościach w czasie przeszłym
            żądaniach, prośbach (w czasie teraźniejszym) - użycie could jest bardziej formalne i grzeczne niż CAN.

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Możliwości, umiejętności w przeszłości:

            I could swim when I was 5 years old.
            My grandmother could speak seven languages.
            When we arrived home, we couldn't open the door.
            Could you understand what he was saying?

            UWAGA !
            Gdy mówimy o OGÓLNYCH możliwościach i umiejętnościach używamy COULD / COULDN'T,
            ale jeśli mówimy o specjalnych okazjach, jednorazowych wyczynach używamy BE ABLE TO

            GENERAL:
            My grandmother COULD speak Spanish.
            My grandmother COULDN'T speak Spanish.

            SPECIFIC OCCASION:
            A man fell into the river yesterday. Luckily, the police WERE ABLE TO save him.
            A man fell into the river yesterday. Unfortunately, the police WEREN'T ABLE TO save him. - to oznacza że próbowali go ratować ale nie byli w stanie go uratować.
            może być również ->  the police COULDN'T save him. - to oznacza że nie podjęli próby ratowania

            --------------------------------------------------------------------

            Żądania, prośby - grzeczniej jest używać słowa COULD w prośbach i żądaniach niż CAN.

            Could you tell me where the bank is, please?
            Could you send me a catalogue, please?

            ===================================================================

            BE ABLE TO

            Możemy używać we wszystkich czasach (oznacza że byłem w stanie coś robić):

            I was able to drive ...
            I will be able to drive ...
            I have been able to drive ...

            także jako bezokolicznik (infinitive):

            I would like to be able to speak Chinese.

            CAN i COULD nie mają formy bezokolicznika, CAN możemy używać tylko w czasie teraźniejszym a COULD w czasie przeszłym.
            We wszystkich pozostałych czasach zamiast CAN / COULD używamy BE ABLE TO:

            I have been able to swim since I was five. (present perfect)
            You will be able to speak English. (future simple)
            I would like to be able to fly an airplane. (infinitive)




        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>Masterclass - Unit 2</part>
        <subpart>2</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Comparatives and Superlatives (Stopniowanie przymiotników)</title>
        <content>
            long - longer - the longest
            short - shorter - the shortest

            large - larger - the largest
            late - later - the latest

            flat - flatter - the flattest
            thin - thinner - the thinnest

            heavy - heavier - the heaviest
            funny - funnier - the funniest

            important - more/less important - the most/least important
            independent - more/less independent - the most/least independent

            clever - cleverer - the cleverest
            narrow - narrower - the narrowest
            moder - more/less modern - the most/least modern

            good - better - the best
            bad - worse - the worst
            far - farther - the farthest

            well - better - the best
            badly - worse - the worst
            much - more - the most
            little - less - the least

            quickly - more/less quickly - the most/least quickly
            carefully - more/less carefully - the most/least carefully
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>Masterclass - Unit 2</part>
        <subpart>2</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>