<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Conditional sentences</title>
        <content>

            Zero conditional.
            =====================================

            Używamy gdy warunek zawsze jest prawdziwy.

            -------------------------------------
            IF + present + present simple
            -------------------------------------

            IF you put paper on fire, it BURNS quickly.
            IF Mike READS on the train, he FEELS sick. (Every time Mike reads on the train, the same thins happens: he feels sick.)
            IF the phone rings, answer it

            Zamiast IF w Zero Conditional można używać WHEN lub WHENEVER.

            =====================================
            First conditional.
            =====================================

            Ten rodzaj trybu warunkowego używamy gdy przewidujemy rezultat jakiegoś wydarzenia (przykłady: 1, 2)
            lub gdy przekonujemy do czegoś, obiecujemy, ostrzegamy, straszymy (przykłady: 3, 4, 5, 6).

            -------------------------------------
            IF + present + future (WILL/MAY/MUST ...)
            -------------------------------------

            1. IF we DON'T LEAVE now, we WILL MISS the train.
            2. IF we LEAVE now, we WON'T NEED TO HURRY.

            3. IF you PASS the exams, we'LL give you a job.
            4. IF you DON'T TURN that music down, you'LL be deaf.
            5. IF we LEAVE now, we MAY CATCH the train.
            6. IF you COME to London again, you MUST CALL AND SEE us.

            =====================================
            Second conditional.
            =====================================

            Ten tryb warunkowy używany jest do spekulacji. (przykłady: 1, 2, 3)
            Używamy go także gdy dajemy komuś porady. (przykłady: 4)
            Zamiast WOULD możemy stosować COULD/MIGHT. (przykład: 5)

            -------------------------------------
            IF + past simple + would/could/might + verb (infinitive)
            -------------------------------------

            1. IF you WENT to AFRICA, you'D HAVE TO HAVE several injection. (It's not likely you'll go to Africa, but it is possible)
            2. You'D FEEL healthier IF you DID more exercise.
            3. IF people DIDN'T DRIVE so fast, there WOULDN'T BE so many accidents.

            4. IF I WERE you, I WOULDN'T DRIVE so fast.

            5. IF you DID more exercise, you MIGHT/COULD FEEL healthier.

            =====================================
            Third conditional.
            =====================================

            W tym trybie spekulujemy na temat sytuacji z przeszłości, które się nie wydarzyły.

            -------------------------------------
            IF + past perfect + would/could/might HAVE + past participle
            -------------------------------------

            If I HAD HAD your address, I WOULD HAVE SENT you a postcard.
            You MIGHT NOT HAVE CRASHED into the bus if you HAD BEEN DRIVING more slowly.

            =====================================
            MIXed conditional.
            =====================================

            Ten tryb warunkowy jest połączeniem 2 i 3 trybu.
            Używamy go gdy mówimy o akcji z przeszłości która ma wpływ na teaźniejszość.

            -------------------------------------
            IF + past perfect + would/could/might
            -------------------------------------

            If I HADN'T BROKEN my leg, I WOULD GO on holiday with you.
            I'D HAVE a better job now, IF I'D WORKED harder when I was at school.

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>Masterclass - Unit 11</part>
        <subpart>1</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>
