<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Gerunds and infinitives</title>
        <content>
            GERUNDS
            ===================================================================

            Gerunds (czaswoniki) są jak rzeczowniki. Tworzy się je przez dodanie -ing do czasownika.
            Używamy ich w następujacy sposób:

            1. Jako podmiot w zdaniu:

            EATING OUT can me expensive

            2. Jako dopełnienie:

            One of my interests is COLLECTING antiques

            3. Po konkretnych czasownikach:

                - Po czasownikach wyrażających uczucie lub niechęć:

                I don't ENJOY SEEING you like this.

                hate, like, love, can't bear, can't stand, dislike

                - Po konkretnych czasownikach:

                admit, appreciate, avoid, can't help, consider, delay, deny, finish, forgive, give up, imagine, involve,
                keep, mind, miss, postpone, put off, prevent, report, resist, risk, suggest

                He ADMITTED cheating on the test.
                I APPRECIATED her helping me.
                He AVOIDED talking to her.
                He CAN'T HELP talking so loudly.
                She CONSIDERED moving to New York.
                He DELAYED doing his taxes.
                He DENIED committing the crime.
                He FINISHED doing his homework.
                He IMAGINES working there one day.
                The job INVOLVES traveling to Japan once a month.
                She KEPT interrupting me.
                Do you MIND waiting here for a few minutes.
                She MISSES living near the beach.
                He POSTPONED returning to Paris.
                He REPORTED her stealing the money.
                He RESISTED asking for help.
                He RISKED being caught.
                They SUGGESTED staying at the hotel.

            4. Po przyimkach (prepositions):

                - Po wszytskich przyimkach:

                It's for opening bottles.

                - Po przymiotnikach + przyimek:

                nervous/worried ABOUT
                bad/good/clever/skilled AT
                sorry/responsible FOR
                interested IN
                capable/afraid/frightened/terrified OF
                bored WITH

                - Po czasownikach + przyimek:

                warn sb ABOUT
                apologize FOR
                arrest sb FOR
                succeed IN
                congratulate sb ON
                insist ON
                be/get use TO, look forward TO, object TO

                My little brother INSISTED on coming with me.

            -------------------------------------------------------------------


            INFINITIVES
            ===================================================================

            1. Po konkretnych czasownikach:

            afford, agree, arrange, ask, appear, attempt, choose, decide, expect, help, hope, intend, learn, manage,
            offer, pretend, promise, refuse, seem

            I can't AFFORD to go on holiday this year.
            Tom AGREED to help me.
            Naomi ARRANGED to stay with her cousin in Miami.
            She ASKED to leave.
            His health APPEARED to be better.
            I CHOSE to help.
            We DECIDED to go to Hawaii.
            They EXPECT to arrive early.
            I hope to BEGIN college this year.
            We INTEND to visit you next spring.
            I LEARNED to speak Japanese when I was a kid.
            He MANAGED to open the door without the key.
            Frank OFFERED to drive us to the supermarket.
            The child PRETENDED to be a monster.
            She PROMISED to stop smoking.
            The guard REFUSED to let them enter the building.
            Nancy SEEMED to be disappointed.

            -------------------------------------------------------------------


            GERUNDS or INFINITIVES (w zależności od kontekstu)
            ===================================================================

            1. Czasowniki: START, BEGIN, CONTINUE mogą być używane jako gerund lub infinitive bez zmiany znaczenia:

            Jeff CONTINUED to overeat/overeating despite the doctor's advice.

            2. Czasowniki: LIKE, PREFER, HATE, LOVE nieco zmieniają znaczenie.

                GERUND jest częściej używany w znaczeniu ogólnym:
                Mary PREFERS EATING out to eating at home.

                INFINITIVE jest uywany gdy podajemy konkretny powód:
                Jane PREFERES TO EAT out because there's no washing-up to do.

            3. Czasowniki: TRY, STOP, REGRET, REMEMBER, FORGET, MEAN, GO ON znacząco zmieniają znaczenie zdania:

                TRY + GERUND - eksperymentować z robieniem czegoś
                TRY GOING to bed earlier and se if that helps

                TRY + INFINITIVE - robić jakiś wysiłek podczas próby o coś
                Sophie's been TRYING TO GET a job since she left shool, but with no success.

                -------------------------------------------------------------------

                STOP + GERUND - zakończyć jakąś aktywność
                STOP TALKING and get on with your work.

                STOP + INFINITIVE - przerwać jedną czynność (którą się wykonywało) i rozpocząć kolejną
                Roger STOPPED (what he was doing) TO HAVE a cup of tea.

                -------------------------------------------------------------------

                REGRET + GERUND - żałować czegoś z przeszłości
                Many people REGRET MARRYING young.

                REGRET + INFINITIVE - z żalem zawiadamiać o czymś co się dopiero ma zamiar powiedzieć
                Dr Taylor REGRETS TO SAY that she is unable to see patients without an appointment.

                -------------------------------------------------------------------

                FORGET / REMEMBER + GERUND - gdy wspominamy/przypominamy sobie jakąś czynność z przeszłości
                I won't FORGET BEING at the Olympic Games as long as I live.
                I remember asking them to come after lunch - pamiętam jak zapraszałem ich aby przyszli po obiedzie.

                FORGET / REMEMBER + INFINITIVE - gdy przypominamy komuś o czymś co ma zrobić
                Ann REMEMBERED TO LOCK all the doors when she went on holiday,
                but she FORGOT TO CLOSE the bathroom window.

                -------------------------------------------------------------------

                GO ON + GERUND - kontunuować robienie czegoś
                I'll GO ON APPLYING for jobs until I'm successful.

                GO ON + INFINITIVE - zakończyć jedną czynność i rozpocząć kolejną
                After seven years of study, Andy WENT ON TO BECOME a doctor

                -------------------------------------------------------------------

                MEAN + GERUND - wymagać czegoś (involve)
                Dieting usually MEANS GIVING UP sweet things.

                MEAN + INFINITIVE - zamierzać, mieć zamiar (intend)
                I MEANT TO SEND you a postcard, but I couldn't remember your address.


        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>Masterclass - Unit 6</part>
        <subpart>1</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>
