<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Relative clauses</title>
        <content>
            Relative clauses jest używany gdy chcemy dodać dodatkowe informacje do zdania.
            Zamiast tworzyć dwa zdania, używamy "relative clauses" aby ułożyć jedno zdanie.

            The man was so boring. He sat next to me the whole journey.
            The man who sat next to me the whole journey was so borning.

            -----------------------------------------
            RELATIVE PRONOUNS - zaimki względne
            -----------------------------------------

            who (whom),
            which,
            that,
            whose,
            where,
            when,
            why

            Wybieramy odpowiedni "relative pronouns" polegając na:

            1. Czy "relative clause" to defining czy non-defining.
            2. Czy odnosi się do osoby czy do rzeczy.
            3. Czy jest podmiotem czy dopełnieniem w zdaniu:


            Subject / Defining / Person:     WHO, THAT
            Subject / Defining / Thing:      WHICH, THAT
            Subject / Non-defining / Person: WHO
            Subject / Non-defining / Thing:  WHICH

            Object / Defining / Person:      0, WHO(M), THAT
            Object / Defining / Thing:       0, WHICH, THAT
            Object / Non-defining / Person:  WHO(M)
            Object / Non-defining / Thing:   WHICH

            Possessive / Defining / Person:     WHOSE (OF WHICH)
            Possessive / Defining / Thing:      WHOSE
            Possessive / Non-defining / Person: WHOSE (OF WHICH)
            Possessive / Non-defining / Thing:  WHOSE

            ===================================================================

            -------------------------------------------
            DEFINING AND NON-DEFINING RELATIVE CLAUSES
            -------------------------------------------

            1. Defining clauses
            -------------------------------------------

            Wtedy gdy informacja jest essencją zdania i bez tej informacji nie wiemy o kim lub o czym jest mowa.

            The man WHO CAME TO THE WEDDING DRESSED IN JEANS is Simon's brother.

            2. Non-defining clauses
            -------------------------------------------

            Gdy informacja nie jest esencją zdania, gdy pominiemy tę informację nadal zdanie ma sens i wiemy o czym
            lub o kim jest mowa.

            Mr White, WHO HAS BEEN HEAD TEACHER, is retiring at the end of term.
            He climbed the mountain wearing only a T-shirt and jeans, WHICH WAS A STUPID THING TO DO.
            We stayed at th Carlton, WHICH IS A FIVE-STAR HOTEL IN THE CITY CENTRE.

            3. Relative clauses and preposition
            -------------------------------------------

            Formal use:

            Defining relative: The man TO WHOM I SPOKE gave me different information.
                               The letter TO WHICH YOU REFER has not been answered.

            Non-defining relative: The hotel manager, TO WHOM I SPOKE ABOUT THE PROBLEM, suggested I write to you.
                                   The fact that hotel was renovation during our stay,
                                   ABOUT WHICH WE HAD NOT BEEN INFORMED, completely ruined our holiday.

            4. Relative clauses after numbers and certain words
            -------------------------------------------

            A. Często NON-DEFINING relative clauses są wprowadzane za pomocą:

            number + OF + all, any, both, each, either, (a) few, many, most, much, neither, none, some

            Dozens of people had been invited, TEN OF WHOM I KNEW.
            I fell asleep during the lecture, MOST OF WHICH WAS INCOMPREHENSIBLE.

            B. DEFINING relative clauses są wprowadzane za pomocą:

            all, any(thing), every(thing), (a) few, little, many, much, no(thing), none, some(thing)

            It was SOMETHING THAT COULD HAVE HAPPENED TO ANYONE.
            It was THE MOST DIFFICULT EXAM (THAT) I'VE EVER TAKEN.

            5. Omitting pronouns from relative clauses
            -------------------------------------------

            Pomijamy RELATIVE PRONOUNS gdy:

            A. DEFINING: gdy zaimek względny (which, who, that) jest dopełnieniem.

            The party 0 I WHENT TO LAST NIGHT didn't finish till late.
            The tree 0 THE COUNCIL CUT DOWN BY MISTAKE was over fifty years old ...

            B. DEFINING: Gdy ta sama osoba z czasownikem BE, usuwamy zaimek i słówko BE.

            The man (WHO IS) STANDING ON HIS OWN OVER THERE is Amy's brother.
            The car (WHICH WAS) USED IN THE ROBBERY was discovered abandoned in a nearby field.

            ===================================================================

        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>Masterclass - Unit 9</part>
        <subpart>1</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>
