<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary>
    <grammary_issue>
        <title>Present Perfect + for / + since</title>
        <content>     
            A. Where do you live now? B. In Manchester.
            A. How long have you lived there? B. I've lived there since 1990
            A. Where do you work B. In a primary school.
            A. how long have you worked there B. I've worked there for five years.

            - Używamy present perfect z for lub since gdy mówimy o akcji/stanie które zaczeły się w przeszłości i trwają do teraz.
            I've lived in M since 1990 = I came to live in M in 1990 an I live in M now.
            - Używamy HOW LONG aby zadać pytanie o czas trwania akcji/stanu
            - Używamy SINCE aby określić POCZĄTEK przedziału czasu (do teraz) since 1990, since last June etc
            - Aby określić przedział czasu w przeszłości (nie do teraz) nie wolno użyć SINCE - UŻYWAMY form 1990 to 2003.
            - Używamy FOR + okres czasu (do teraz) - I've had this car for three months. 
            - Aby określić przedział czasu w przesłości również możemy użyć FOR - He was married for two years (= He's not married now)
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 2 Pre Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7A</subpart>
    </grammary_issue>
    <grammary_issue>
        <title>Present Perfect czy Past simple</title>
        <content>
            How long has Tarantino been a director? He has been a director since the 1980s.
            How many films has he made? He's made six films
            - Używamy present perfect + how long?, for, sunce gdy mówimy o przedziale czasu który trwa do teraz.
            How long have you been married? I've been married for 10 years (= I'm married now)

            How long was Hitchcock a director? he was a director for 50 years.
            How many films did he make? He made 52 films
            - Używamy Past Simple + how long? lub for gdy mówimy o zakończonych przedziałach czasu w przeszłości.
            How long was he married? he was married for two tears (= He's no married now)
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 2 Pre Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7B</subpart>
    </grammary_issue>
    <grammary_issue>
        <title>USE TO/ DIDN'T USE TO (KIEDYŚ) | USED TO/ DIDN"T USE TO + Infinitive</title>
        <content>
            I, You, He, She, We etc. USED TO wear glasses
            Ja, Ty, On, Ona, My itd. kiedyś nosiliśmy okulary

            DID (I, you, she, they) USE TO wear glasses
            Czy (ja, ty, ona, oni) kiedyś nosili okulary?

            Yes, (I, We) did
            Tak, (Ja, My) nosiliśmy

            No, (She, They) didn't
            Nie, (Ona, Oni) nie nosili

            - Używamy used to/didn't use to + bezokolicznik dla wydarzeń które były powtarzane 
            przez wiele razy w jakimś przedziale czasu w przesłości, ale obecnie są nieprawdziwe (teraz tego nie robimy)
            np. czynności które miały miejsce gdy byłeś dzieckiem.
            I used to have long hair. I used to play in the street. I didn't use to have a TV.
            - Zamiennie można użyć czasy przeszłego (Simple Past) - I had long hair when I was a child.

            - USED TO - używamy tylko dla przyzwyczajeń z przeszłości - do obecych przyzwyczajeń używamy USUALLY
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 2 Pre Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7C</subpart>
    </grammary_issue>
    <grammary_issue>
        <title>PASSIVE VOICE</title>
        <content>
            be (is, are, was, were) + past participle (III Forma)

            Present - Teraźniejszość
            +
            Risotto is made with rice.
            These offices are cleaned every morning.
            -
            It isn't made with pasta.
            They aren't cleaned on Saturday.
            ?
            Is it made with meat?
            Are they cleaned on Sundays?

            Past - Przeszłość
            +
            Guernica was painted by Picasso.
            The pyramids were built by the Egyptians.
            -
            It wasn't painted by Dali.
            They weren't built by the Greeks.
            ?
            When was it painted?
            Why were they built?

            Zdanie można powiedzieć na dwa sposoby w trybie czynnym i biernym.
            Picasso painted Guernica(active)
            Guernica was painted by Picasso

            W tybie czynnym akcentujemy kto był autorem obrazu,
            w trybie biernym bardziej akcentujemy obraz - to na nim się skupiamy.

            Passive - można użyć także wtedy kiedy nie znamy wykonawcy jakiejś  akcji
            My car was stolen last week

            Present Passive - tworzymy (am, is, are) + III forma czasownika
            Past Passive - tworzymy (was, where) + III forma czasownika

            BY - używamy by aby wskazać kto wykonał daną akcje:
            The Lord of the Rings was written by Tolkien.
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 2 Pre Intermediate - Unit 7</part>
        <subpart>7D</subpart>
    </grammary_issue>
</grammary>