<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Passive (all forms), it is said that .. he is thought to ... etc</title>
        <content>   
            1. Passive (all form)
            
            Present simple
            Murderer ARE usually sentencED to life imprisonment.
            
            Present Continuous
            The trial IS BEING HELD at the moment.
            
            Present Perfect
            My car HAS BEEN stolen.
            
            Past Simple
            Jim WAS ARRESTED last month.
            
            Past Continuous
            The cinema WAS BEING REBUILT when it was set on fire.
            
            Past Perfect
            We saw that one of the windows HAD BEEN BROKEN.
            
            Future
            The prisoner WILL BE releasED next month.
            The verdict IS GIOING TO BE GIVEN tommorow.
            
            invinitive with TO
            People used TO BE imprisonED for stealing bread.
            
            infinitive without TO
            You can BE finED for parking here.
            
            gerund - rzeczowik odczasownikowy (ING)
            He paid a fine to avoid being sent to jail.
            
            Używamy gdy checmy mówić o wydarzeniu / akcji ale nie istotne jest kto wykonywał akcję / brał udział.
            Jeśli chcemy jednak wspomnieć kto wykonywał danę akcję dodajemy BY. Prison sentences are decided BY judges.
            Aczkolwiek w stronie biernej zasadą jest nie wspominanie przez kogo została wykonana czynność / akcja.
            
            ====================================================================
            
            it is said that ..., he i thought to ..., etc.
            
            1. They say that the company may close.
            It is said that company may close.
            
            People think that prices will go up.
            It is thought that prices will go up.
            
            2. People say the man is in 40s.
            The man is said to be in 40s.
            
            The police bealived he has left the country.
            He is belived to have left the country.
            
            Używany najczęściej w TV, newsach i raportach.
            1. IT IS SAID, BELIVED etc. + THAT + reszta zdania
            2. HE, The man etc. (podmiot) + is said, belived, etc + to + infinitive (np. TO BE, TO WORK) (bezokolicznik) LUB Perfect infinitive (np. TO HAVE BEEN).
            
            ------------------------------------
            
            Przykłady dla poszczególnych czasów:
            
            Present Simple
            People belive HE WORKS in Africa.
            It is belived THAT he works in Africa.
            He is belived TO WORK in Africa.
            
            Present Continous
            They think she IS tryING to write a book.
            It is thought THAT she is trying to write a book.
            She is thought TO BE TRYING to wite a book.
            
            Simple Past, Past perfect, Present Perfect
            People think he escaped from prison.
            It is thought THAT he escaped from prison.
            He is thought TO HAVE ESCAPED from prison.
            
            Past Continous, Past perfect contonous, present perfect continous
            They say she was crying when she was leaving.
            It is said THAT she was crying when she was leaving.
            She is said TO HAVE BEEN CRYING when she was leaving.
            
            Passive
            They claim that she was murdered.
            She is claimed TO HAVE BEEN MURDERED.
            
            --------------------------------------
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>SO / SUCH (A) ... THAT</title>
        <content>  
            bla
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>tyt</part>
        <subpart>3B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>tyt</title>
        <content>
            bla
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>