<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Passive (all forms), it is said that .. he is thought to ... etc</title>
        <content>   
            1. Passive (all form)
            
            Present simple
            Murderer ARE usually sentencED to life imprisonment.
            
            Present Continuous
            The trial IS BEING HELD at the moment.
            
            Present Perfect
            My car HAS BEEN stolen.
            
            Past Simple
            Jim WAS ARRESTED last month.
            
            Past Continuous
            The cinema WAS BEING REBUILT when it was set on fire.
            
            Past Perfect
            We saw that one of the windows HAD BEEN BROKEN.
            
            Future
            The prisoner WILL BE releasED next month.
            The verdict IS GIOING TO BE GIVEN tommorow.
            
            invinitive with TO
            People used TO BE imprisonED for stealing bread.
            
            infinitive without TO
            You can BE finED for parking here.
            
            gerund - rzeczowik odczasownikowy (ING)
            He paid a fine to avoid being sent to jail.
            
            Używamy gdy checmy mówić o wydarzeniu / akcji ale nie istotne jest kto wykonywał akcję / brał udział.
            Jeśli chcemy jednak wspomnieć kto wykonywał danę akcję dodajemy BY. Prison sentences are decided BY judges.
            Aczkolwiek w stronie biernej zasadą jest nie wspominanie przez kogo została wykonana czynność / akcja.
            
            ====================================================================
            
            it is said that ..., he i thought to ..., etc.
            
            1. They say that the company may close.
            It is said that company may close.
            
            People think that prices will go up.
            It is thought that prices will go up.
            
            2. People say the man is in 40s.
            The man is said to be in 40s.
            
            The police bealived he has left the country.
            He is belived to have left the country.
            
            Używany najczęściej w TV, newsach i raportach.
            1. IT IS SAID, BELIVED etc. + THAT + reszta zdania
            2. HE, The man etc. (podmiot) + is said, belived, etc + to + infinitive (np. TO BE, TO WORK) (bezokolicznik) LUB Perfect infinitive (np. TO HAVE BEEN).
            
            ------------------------------------
            
            Przykłady dla poszczególnych czasów:
            
            Present Simple
            People belive HE WORKS in Africa.
            It is belived THAT he works in Africa.
            He is belived TO WORK in Africa.
            
            Present Continous
            They think she IS tryING to write a book.
            It is thought THAT she is trying to write a book.
            She is thought TO BE TRYING to wite a book.
            
            Simple Past, Past perfect, Present Perfect
            People think he escaped from prison.
            It is thought THAT he escaped from prison.
            He is thought TO HAVE ESCAPED from prison.
            
            Past Continous, Past perfect contonous, present perfect continous
            They say she was crying when she was leaving.
            It is said THAT she was crying when she was leaving.
            She is said TO HAVE BEEN CRYING when she was leaving.
            
            Passive
            They claim that she was murdered.
            She is claimed TO HAVE BEEN MURDERED.
            
            --------------------------------------
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Likely and Probably</title>
        <content>  
            Likely (adj.) - przymiotnik
            
            be + likely + infinitives
            She is likely to be off work for a long time. (Ona najprawdopodobnie będzie długo bez pracy)
            I don't think the boss is very likely to agree.
            That isn't likely to happen in the near future. (To nie jest prawdopodobne że zdaży się w najbliższej przyszłości)
            
            be + likely + that
            Gdy czasownik BE jest w zdaniu można też użyć takiej konstrukcji:
            
            It isn't likely that we will be here this weekend
            = We probably won't be here this weekend.
            
            It isn't very likely that I'll be taking part in the campaign.
            = I probably won't be taking part in the campaingn.
            
            --------------------------------------
            
            Probably (adverb) - przysłówek
            
            Używamy PRZED głównym czasownikiem w zdaniach TWIERDZĄCYCH.
            Używamy PRZED pomocniczym czasownikiem (auxiliary verb: will, won't) w zdaniach PRZECZĄCYCH
            
            She will probably be off work for a long time.
            They probably won't be here before 6.00.
            I will probably be home late tonight.
            I probably won't be home late tonight.
            --------------------------------------
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Future Perfect and Future Continuous</title>
        <content>  
            Future perfect:
            
            WILL + HAVE + III forma (past participle) 
            
            Używamy gdy chcemy powiedzieć że coś zostanie zrobione do konkretnej chwili w przyszłości
            I'LL HAVE finishED this article by Friday, so I'll email it to you then.
            
            Ten czas jest często używany z:
            BY (by Saturday/March/2030 - najpóźniej do soboty/marca/2030)
            IN (in two weeks / in two months - w dwa tygodnie, w dwa miesiące)
            
            BY + a time expression = at latest - najpóźniej do
            IN - in six months / in six months' time
            
            --------------------------------------
            
            Future Continuous:
            
            WILL BE + VERB + -ING
            
            Używamy gdy czynność będzie wykonywana w danym czasie w przyszłości.
            Don't phone between 7 and 8 as we WILL BE havING supper then.
            This time next week I WILL BE lyING on the beach.
            
            Czasami używamy future continuous jak present continous - mówiąc o planach lub decyzjach.
            I WILL BE goING to the supermarket later.
            
            --------------------------------------
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3C</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Conditionals and Future time clauses (with all present and future forms)</title>
        <content>
            Zero conditional
            
            IF + Present Simple, Present Simple
            
            Używamy gdy mówimy że coś jest zawsze prawdą (np. zjawiska fizyczne)
            IF YOU WANT to be fit, YOU HAVE TO do exercise every day.
            IF YOU DON'T WATER plants, they die.
            
            Można używać także Present Continous lub Present Perfect (ważne aby był to czas PRESENT)
            If your muscles ACHE every day, you ARE probably doING too much excercise.
            If you HAVEN'T BEEN to London, you HAVEN'T livED.
            
            --------------------------------------
            
            First Conditional
            
            IF + PRESENT Simple/Continous/Perfect, FUTURE FORM will/going to/future perfect/future continous
            
            If the photos ARE good, I WILL SEND them to you.
            If YOU ARE NOT GOING, I'M NOT GOING TO GO either.
            If I HAVEN"T COME BACK by 9, START dinner without me.
            I WILL HAVE FINISHED IN an hour if YOU DON'T disturb me.
            
            --------------------------------------
            
            Future time clauses
            
            Gdy mówimy o przyszłości używamy PRESENT TENSE po:
            
            as soon as,
            when,
            until, 
            unless,
            before,
            after,
            in case.
            
            Używamy IN CASE gdy robimy coś na przyszłość.
            Porównaj znaczenie z IF i IN CASE:
            
            I'll take a jacket if it's cold = I won't take one if it's not cold.
            I'll take a jacket IN CASE it's cold = I'll take it anyway because it might be cold.
            
            
            
             
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 3</part>
        <subpart>3C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>