<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<grammary_roles>
    <grammary>
        <title>Unreal conditionals</title>
        <content>   
            SECOND CONDITIONAL SENTENCES:
            
            IF + PAST SIMPLE, WOULD/WOULDN'T + INFINITIVE
            
            
            Używamy 2 conditional gdy mówimy o HIPOTETYCZNCH sytuacjach odnoszących się do PRZYSZŁOŚCI
            
            If there WAS a fire in this hotel, it WOULD BE very difficult to escape.
            I wouldn't live in the country if I didn't have a car.
            
            W 2 conditional można używać PAST CONTINOUS, a w drugiej części zdania COULD lub MIGHT zamias WOULD
            
            If you weren't making so much noise, I COULD concentrate better.
            
            
            Można używać dla I, He, SHE + WAS/WERE ale musi być IF I WERE YOU itd.
            
            If he WAS / WERE here, he WOULD know what to do.
            If I WERE you, I'd make Jimmy wear a helmet.
            
            ====================================================================
            
            THIRD CONDITIONAL SENTENSES:
            
            IF + PAST PERFECT, WOULD/WOULDN'T HAVE + PAST PARTICIPLE (3-cia forma)
            
            
            Używamy 3 conditional gdy mówimy o HIPOTETYCZNYCH sytuacjach z PRZESZŁOŚCI i ich KONSEKWENCJACH w przeszłości
            
            IF you HAD STUDIED more, you WOULD HAVE DOE better in the exams.
            I WOULDN'T HAVE BEEN late IF I HADN'T OVERSLEPT.
            
            Można używać w 3 conditional PAST PERFECT CONTINUOUS. 
            Można używać COULD HAVE lub MIGHT HAVE zamiast WOULD HAVE.
            
            He WOULD HAVE died if he HADN'T BEEN WEARING a helmet.
            IF they HAD know you were coming, they MIGHT HAVE stayed longer.
            
            ====================================================================
            
            SECOND or THIRD conditional?
            
            1. If you STUDIED more, you would probably pass the exam.
            2. If you had studied more, you would probably have passed the exam
            
            1. Nie uczysz się wystarczająco dużo, musisz uczyć się więcej bo oblejesz test (w przyszłości).
            2. Nie uczyłeś się wystarczająco dużo, dlatego oblałeś test.
            
            ---------------------------------
            
            Czasami można zmieszać 2 i 3 conditional gdy hipotetyczna sytuacja 
            z przeszłości ma obecne/przyszłe konsekwencje
            
            He wouldn't be so relaxed if he hadn't finished the exams.
            
            ---------------------------------
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4A</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Past Modals</title>
        <content>  
            MUST / MIGHT / CAN'T + HAVE + PAST PARTICIPLE (3 forma)
            
            
            MUST HAVE - gdy jesteśmy PEWNI że coś jest PRAWDĄ
            
            I MUST HAVE PASSED the exam. I'm sure I got all the answers right.
            Przeciwieństwo do MUST HAVE jest CAN'T HAVE
            You MUST HAVE SEEN something. You were there when it happened.
            
            ====================================================================
            
            MIGHT HAVE / COULD HAVE- gdy coś jest MOŻLIWE
            Przeczenie robimy przez dodanie NOT pomiędzu MIGHT i HAVE = MIGHT NOT HAVE
            
            Somebody MIGHT HAVE STOLEN your wallet whem you were getting off the train.
            He still hasn't arrived. I MIGHT NOT HAVE given him the right direction
            
            ====================================================================
            
            CANT'T HAVE - gdy jesteśmy PEWNI że coś NIE JEST PRAWDĄ, NIE WYDARZYŁO SIĘ.
            Można również użyć COULDN'T HAVE.
            
            They CAN'T HAVE GONE to bed yet. It's only ten o'clock.
            They CAN'T HAVE SEEN us. It was too dark.
            
            ====================================================================
            
            SHOULD + HAVE + PAST PARTICIPLE (3 forma)
            
            Używamy SHOULD + HAVE + PP gdy mówimy że ktoś postąpił niesłusznie.
            Nie powinnien tak postąpić.
            
            It's my fault. I SHOULD HAVE TOLD you earlier.
            We SHOULDN'T HAVE TURNED left at the traffic light.
            
            ---------------------------------
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4B</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Look / feel / smell / sound / taste</title>
        <content> 
            
            Używamy look, feel, etc + ADJ. (przymiotnik) 
            
            1. She look tired. That smells good. These jeans don't feel comfortable.
            
            ---------------------------------
            
            Używamy look, feel, etc + LIKE + NOUN (rzeczownik)
            
            2. He looks LIKE his father. This material feels LIKE silk. This tastes LIKE tea, not coffee.
            
            !UWAGA!
            FEEL LIKE może znaczyć WANT/WOULD LIKE (chcieć)
            I don't FEEL LIKE GOING OUT = I don't WANT TO GO OUT.
            
            ---------------------------------
            
            Używamy look, feel, etc + AS IF + clause (całe zdanie opisujące) 
            (AS IF == jak gdyby)
            
            3. She looks AS IF SHE'S BEEN CRYING. It smells AS iF STH'S BURNING. It spunds AS IF IT'S RAINING.
            
            ---------------------------------
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4C</subpart>
    </grammary>
    <grammary>
        <title>Would RATHER, Had BETTER</title>
        <content>
            
            HAD BETTER = should
            Had better jest mocniejsze od should i zazwyczaj używamy jako ostrzeżenia.
            
            Używamy HAD BETTER + INFINITIVE (BEZ to)
            
            You HAD BETTER hurry up.
            You HAD BETTER NOT tell your parents. (nie można użyć hadn't)
            
            ====================================================================
            
            WOULD RATHER = prefer (woleć, preferować)
            
            Używamy WOULD RATHER + INFINITIVE (BEZ to)
            
            I WOULD RATHER go on holiday in July this year.
            WOULD you RATHER stay in or go out tonight?
            I WOULD RATHER NOT come to the meeting. (nie można użyć I would NOT rather)
            
        </content>
        <comment>
        </comment>
        <part>New English File 4 Upper Intermediate - Unit 4</part>
        <subpart>4C</subpart>
    </grammary>
</grammary_roles>